Guide to the Paul Shoup Papers, 1928-1946
Department of Special Collections
Paul Shoup Papers,
1928-1946
Special Collections M057
Shoup, Paul
4.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
The papers of Paul Shoup are the gift of his sons, Carl Sumner Shoup, professor of economics at Columbia University, and the late Jack Wilson Shoup, former Secretary of the Stanford Alumni Association. They were presented to the Stanford Library in the fall of 1961.
BIOGRAPHY
Paul Shoup, son of Timothy and Sarah Sumner Shoup, was born in San Bernardino, California on January 8, 1874. While still in school, he worked delivering newspapers and later as a local correspondent for a Los Angeles paper. He was graduated from San Bernardino High School in 1891 and afterwards obtained a clerical job in the mechanical department of the Atchinson, Topeka and Santa Fe Railway at San Bernardino.
In 1892, young Paul began his forty-seven year career with the Southern Pacific Company as a ticket clerk in the San Bernardino office. Shoup quickly learned other aspects of the business and worked in the telegraph and freight offices before going into the general office traffic service. Miss Rose Wilson became Mrs. Paul Shoup on December 1, 1900. The Shoups had three children: Carl Sumner, Jack Wilson, and Louise.
In the year following his marriage, Shoup became district freight and passenger agent at San Jose, his first official position. He rose rapidly in the traffic department becoming assistant general freight and passenger agent and an executive of the line at Portland, Oregon. When the earthquake and fire struck San Francisco in 1906, Shoup returned from Portland to serve on the board directing rehabilitation work.
In 1910 Shoup was appointed assistant general manager in charge of the railroad's municipal and inter-urban electric lines in several California cities. Two years later he was made president of the Pacific Electric Railway Company. With the outbreak of World War I, the government took over the operation of the nation's railroads and Shoup was made vice president in charge of the property interests of Southern Pacific and its affiliated and proprietary concerns.
The Southern Pacific Company named Paul Shoup vice president and assistant to the president in 1920, and in 1925, he was appointed executive vice president. In 1929 he became president and in 1932, vice chairman of the board with offices in New York. He retired from the vice chairmanship and Southern Pacific in 1938 to serve as president of Southern Californians, Inc., an employer group organized to "fight racketeering in labor relations."
Shoup had many interests besides the railroad industry. One of his earliest ambitions had been to become a professional writer, and in his early career had had a number of stories published. He published numerous articles and made speeches on a variety of subjects connected with his business and political interests. According to various newspaper accounts of his career, Shoup is supposed to have been one of the initial founders of "Sunset Magazine"--originally a railroadmen's trade journal--and to have been instrumental in building it to become one of the West's leading popular magazines.
Paul Shoup was also president of the Pacific Oil Company and Associated 0il Company and served on the boards of several other oil, land, gas, electric, and railroad companies, including Tide Water Oil. He wrote and conferred a great deal with Congressional and governmental agencies on labor and management problems, ways to reduce the effects of the Depression, and spoke out against the Social Security Act and parts of the Interstate Commerce Act. A Republican in politics, he was very active in the campaign of Alfred M. Landon for President in 1935-36.
Shoup belonged to a number of clubs, including the Bohemian, the Bankers (New York), the Pacific Union (San Francisco), and the Jonathan. He was President of the Merchants and Manufacturers Association, Inc. and was a member of the board of trustees of the San Francisco Conservatory of Music, Inc. and Stanford University, where both his sons received their undergraduate degrees. After a long, active and varied career, Paul Shoup died in California on July 30, 1946.
Most of this biographical material is drawn from
Who's Who in America, vol. 23, 1944-1945
and various newspaper clippings found in the collection.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Paul Shoup collection contains some 7,500 items, by rough estimate, and covers primarily his terms as president and vice chairman of the Southern Pacific Company between 1929 and 1938. There are some items dated 1928 and some pertaining to Southern Californians, Inc., which he joined after retiring from Southern Pacific in 1938. There are also a few items dated as late as 1945 and 1946. The collection is made up, in part, of personal and business correspondence, various business papers and reports, minutes of meetings of stockholders and boards of directors, financial statements, annual reports, governmental and Congressional documents, Depression relief proposals, clippings, memos, and Shoup's own articles and addresses.
The subject matter covered is rich and varied. In the area of business there are the railroad and oil companies of which the outstanding are Southern Pacific and Tide Water Oil Company. There are also the directors' and stockholders' meetings and the J. Paul Getty proxie fight. Agreements with persons such as R. Stanley Dollar and organizations such as the Calmexico Syndicate and the Mission Corporation also appear.
In politics, Shoup was a Republican. He was a personal friend of Herbert Hoover and corresponded with him on numerous subjects. There are some Hoover autograph letters in the collection including one on a White House letterhead. Shoup was also active in Alf Landon's 1935-36 campaign for the Presidency against Roosevelt and there is a folder of material as well as a number of clippings relating to that subject.
Other subjects can be described as having both political and business facets. Correspondence about the Reconstruction Finance Corporation and with Jesse Jones, articles against portions of the Interstate Commerce Act and the Social Security Act, and Shoup's own indictment along with several oil companies by the federal government for violation of anti-trust legislation, can be placed in this category. The correspondence also points up how much effort in terms of time and money was spent by bankers and railroad executives to find some plan for stemming the Depression and increasing employment.
There is also a fair amount of correspondence relating to StanfordUniversity. As the father of two alumni and a member of the Board of Trustees, Shoup had an active interest in the school. He helped to finance the Hoover Library and the Children's Convalescent Home. During the Depression, he was concerned about the problem of bolstering finances of the University.
Some of the many important names which appear in the correspondence are given below. Arthur Ballantine, Undersecretary of the Treasury; Clarence Bamberger, Associated Oil Distributing Company; Ernest Bamberger, railroad and mining in Utah; Harry Chandler, president of the Times-Mirror Company of Los Angeles; Denver Church, U.S. House of Representatives, 9th District of California, 1933; Royal S. Copeland., U.S. Senator from New York and chairman of the Commerce Committee, 1937; D. A. Crawford, president of the Pullman Company; W. H. Crocker, banker of San Francisco; Joseph Di Giorgio, Di Giorgio Fruit Corporation of New York; J. S. Douglas of Douglas, Arizona; Lewis Williams Douglas, U.S. House of Representatives from Arizona; John Dickinson, assistant Secretary, Department of Commerce; Fred J. Fisher, president of Fisher Body Corporation, Detroit; Herbert Fleishhacker, banker of San Francisco; Carl R. Gray, president of the Union Pacific System; John Hamilton, chairman of the Republican National Committee, 1936-37; L. 0. Head, President of Railway Express Agency, New York; Herbert Hoover, President of the United States, 1929-32; George Houston, president of Baldwin Locomotive Works; William Humphrey, president of Associated Oil Company and Tide Water Oil Company; Hiram Johnson, U.S. Senator from California; Jesse H. Jones, chairman of the R.F.C.; K. R. Kingsbury, president of Standard Oil of California; R. P. Lamont, Secretary of Commerce, 1932; Alfred M. Landon, Governor of Kansas and Presidential candidate; Clarence Lea, U.S. House of Representatives, lst District of California, 1936; Charles Mahaffie, Commissioner of I.C.C., 1934; Eugene Meyer, publisher of the "Washington Post"; Daniel C. Jackling, president and director of Mesabi Iron Company; Ogden MiIls, Secretary of the Treasury, 1932; Walter Newton, secretary to President Hoover; Carl Rott, secretary to Governor Landon; Alfred P. Sloan, president of General Motors Corporation; Ray Lyman Wilbur, Secretary of the Interior and President of Stanford University; and Owen D. Young, chairman of the Banking and Industrial Committee,1932.
CONTAINER LIST
- CORRESP. IN. A.- M (Box 1, Folder 1-14)
- CORRESP. IN. N - Y (Box 2, Folder 15-20)
- CORRESP. OUT. 1928 -1935 May 29 (Box 2, Folder 22-38)
- CORRESP. OUT. 1935 June 1-1946 Jan. 14 and n.d. (Box 3, Folder 39-53)
- GENERAL AND RELATED CORRESP. A - R -not to Shoup, arranged by sender (Box 3, Folder 54-61)
- GENERAL AND RELATED CORRESP. S - Y (Box 4, Folder 62-63)
- GENERAL AND RELATED CORRESP. -unsigned, arranged by recipient (Box 4, Folder 64)
- OUT CORRESP. RE: STANFORD - 1931 Apr.-1946 July 1 (Box 4, Folder 65-70)
- IN CORRESP. RE: STANFORD - A - Y (Box 4, Folder 71-75)
- GEN. CORRESP. RE: STANFORD - 1931 Jan. 4-1946 May 20 (Box 4, Folder 76)
- RAILROADS, GEN. - business reports, etc. and descriptions of smaller and branch roads (Box 5, Folder 77)
- SOUTHERN PACIFIC RAILROAD - business papers (Box 5, Folder 78)
- SOUTHERN PACIFIC RAILROAD -"Application to the Reconstruction Finance Corporation for Loan", 1933 Mar. 15,bound (Box 5, Folder 79)
- RAILROAD REPORTS - ST. LOUIS SOUTHWESTERN RR -legal testimony and reorganization plans (Box 5, Folder 80)
- CALMEXICO - appointments, agreements and etc. (Box 5, Folder 81)
- TIDE WATER OIL CO. - Getty proxie fight, mergers and other business papers (Box 5, Folder 82)
- TIDE WATER OIL CO. - Agreements and reorganization matters (Box 5, Folder 83)
- TIDE WATER OIL CO. - Misc. business papers and more re: Getty (Box 5, Folder 84)
- MISSION CORPORATION (Oil) - reports, etc. (Box 5, Folder 85)
- TIDE WATER OIL CO. -"Application to Securities and Exchange Commission for Permanent Registration under Section 12 (b) of the Securities and Exchange Act of 1934 of Securities Temporarily Registered", -bound (Box 5, Folder 86)
- TIDE WATER ASSOCIATED OIL CO. - bound, same as [folder] 86 (Box 5, Folder 87)
- AGREEMENTS - between companies and persons (Box 6, Folder 88)
- LETTERS TO STOCKHOLDERS AND DIRECTORS (Box 6, Folder 89)
- NOTICES OF MEETINGS, A - S (Box 6, Folder 90-91)
- NOTICES OF MEETINGS AND PROXIES - Tide Water Oil Co., 1932 Mar. 3-1938 June 9 (Box 6, Folder 92)
- NOTICES OF MEETINGS, W (Box 6, Folder 93)
- MINUTES OF DIRECTORS - Calif. College in China, Calif. Palace-Legion of Honor (Box 6, Folder 94)
- MINUTES OF MEETINGS - Calmexico Petroleum, 2 committees; Internat'l Society of Christian Endeavor (Box 6, Folder 95)
- MINUTES OF MEETINGS - Pacific Fruit Express, Southern Pacific Railway (Box 6, Folder 96)
- MINUTES OF MEETINGS - St. Louis Southwestern Railway, 1934-35;Tide Water Oil Co., 1932-36 (Box 6, Folder 97)
- FINANCIAL STATEMENTS - Tide Water Oil, 1927-37 (Box 7, Folder 98)
- FINANCIAL STATEMENTS - Oil Companies (Box 7, Folder 99)
- FINANCIAL STATEMENTS - Southern Pacific Railway, Aug., 1932-Feb., 1938 (Box 7, Folder 100)
- FINANCIAL STATEMENTS - St. Louis Southwestern Railway, 1931-1938 (Box 7, Folder 101)
- FINANCIAL STATEMENTS - Misc. Railroad, gas and electric, 1934-1936 (Box 7, Folder 102)
- ANNUAL REPORTS I - general (Box 7, Folder 103)
- ANNUAL REPORTS II Tide Water Oil, 1931-1938 (Box 7, Folder 104)
- BANKING - Debt and Credit (Box 8, Folder 105)
- GOVERNMENT AND CONGRESSIONAL - Bills, Acts, Reports, etc. (Box 8, Folder 106)
- DEPRESSION - R.F.C. and others, various proposals and plans to relieve it (Box 8, Folder 107)
- PRINTED MATTER - Misc. (Box 8, Folder 108)
- LANDON CAMPAIGN, 1935-1936 (Box 8, Folder 109)
- BOHEMIAN CLUB (Box 9, Folder 110)
- SHOUP ARTICLES - printed and typescripts, 1931-1945 (Box 9, Folder 111)
- MISC. CLUBS - notices, etc. (Box 9, Folder 112)
- U. S. CHAMBER OF COMMERCE (Box 9, Folder 113)
- SHOUP LECTURES -- typed with handwritten notes and drafts, 1930-1936 and n.d. (Box 9, Folder 114-115)
- NATIONAL CONFERENCE OF BUSINESS AND INDUSTRIAL COMMITTEES (Box 9, Folder 116)
- ORGANIZATIONS AND INSTITUTIONS - notices, meetings, etc. (Box 9, Folder 117)
- TRANSPORTATION ASSOCIATION OF AMERICA (Box 9, Folder 118)
- PERSONAL - business cards, invitations, etc. (Box 9, Folder 119)
- W. J. WOLLMAN & CO. WEEKLY LETTER, 1934-1936- much material by Shoup (Box 9, Folder 120)
- LISTS - Shoup's memberships, organizations, contacts, etc. (Box 10, Folder 121)
- Clippings - re: Shoup, 1929-38, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 122)
- PUBLICITY FILE ON SHOUP RETIREMENT FROM VICE CHAIRMANSHIP OF SOUTHERN PACIFIC -bound clippings (Box 10, Folder 123)
- CLIPPINGS - general (Box 10, Folder 124)
- DATED MEMOS, MSS, AND TYPESCRIPTS OF (Box 10, Folder 125)
- UNDATED MEMOS AND MSS (Box 10, Folder 126)
- SOUTHERN CALIFORNIANS, INC. (Box 10, Folder 127)
- MISC. - business (Box 10, Folder 128)
- MISC. - Shoup, personal interests (Box 10, Folder 129)
- FRAGMENTS (Box 10, Folder 130)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Materials withdrawn from the collection: Minutes of the Board of Trustees of Stanford University, Stanford Associates publications, and miscellaneous related Stanford publications were removed and placed in the Stanford Collection.